<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dean Markwick</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2014 22:19:27 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2014 22:19:27 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Playing About with ggplot</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve turned the spellchecker on right away for this post. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After spending the last few hours playing around with some data in R, I’ve managed to produce my first pretty looking graphic using ggplot2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main complication in producing this was fiddling around with the dataframe, getting it in the correct format so that the different colours of the line came out automatically. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, it started off as: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Timestep | Zero | One | Two  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However this gave some complications; when ggplot was grouping the data, I had to refactor the data to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Timestep | Population | Mutation 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This meant that I didn’t have to start manually setting colours, instead it was all decided for me. 
I like to follow the LaTeX school of thought by letting the software decide on the aesthetics that work best, rather that leaving it up to the user. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, it resulted in the following plot: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/InitialDemoGraph280914.png&quot; alt=&quot;First with ggplot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data came from a basic and rough implementation of the Gillespie Algorithm.
More comments on the physics behind it to follow.  &lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2014 23:46:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/2014/09/28/Playing-About-With-ggplot.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2014/09/28/Playing-About-With-ggplot.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>That First Blog Post</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After finally finding some spare time I’ve got round to creating my own website/blog. Let it be a place for rambling about anything I encounter and my learning process on this web design front.&lt;br /&gt;
My main accomplishment today was managing to create my own LinkedIn sprite and link to compliment the github one down below. It involved tinkering with the SVG file and clawing at the basic HTML knowledge receding in my brain from year 7. But I’ve managed to implement it, maybe in the future once I’m a bit more confident I’ll try and get it incorporated into the basic theme, possibly my first open source contribution. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow’s priority is to see if you can get a spell checker in Vim and overcome my Achilles heel of abysmal spelling. But for now, lets hit commit and make sure it works once uploaded.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;21/09/14 Update. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turned on the spell checker and corrected the entire post. Way too many mistakes to be proud of; still another learning point. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2014 22:08:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/2014/09/19/The-First-Blog-Post.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2014/09/19/The-First-Blog-Post.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
